

Kale-ab Tessera

Machine Learning Engineer / Researcher



+27 766806878



kaleabtessera.com



kaleabtessera@gmail.com

About me —

Kale-ab is a young, bright and ambitious Machine Learning Engineer and Researcher. He is adaptable and open to learn new concepts in Machine Learning and AI in order to build on his previous knowledge. He considers a great work ethic and his ability to think innovatively as his greatest strengths.

Skills ——

Deep Learning

Pytorch, Scikit-learn

Tensorflow, Keras

Flask, Django

Python

SQL,NoSQL

Amazon AWS, Google GCP

Mathematics, Quantitative Reasoning

(*)[The skill scale is from 0 (Fundamental Awareness) to 6 (Good Understanding).]

Education

Msc in Computer Science, Focusing on Deep Learning

2018 - 2019

University of Witwatersrand

Research

Title - Learning Compact, General-Purpose Neural Network Architectures.

Topics - Theory of Deep Learning, Neural Architecture Search, AutoML.

Lab - Robotics, Autonomous Intelligence and Learning lab.

Supervisor - Dr. Benjamin Rosman.

Coursework - 86% First year Average.

Adaptive Computation and Machine Learning, Reinforcement Learning, Robotics, Artificial Intelligence, Large Scale Optimization for Data Science and High Performance Computer and Scientific Data Management.

Honours in Computer Science, Cum Laude

2016 - 2016

University of Pretoria

Honours in Computer Science.

B.Sc. Computer Science

2013 - 2015

University of Pretoria

The BSc (CS) degree emphasises the understanding of computer science fundamentals by offering a wide variety of computer science and mathematics courses.

PEPPS College

2008 - 2012

Polokwane

IEB Private School.

Research Committees

Black in AI

2017,2018

Reviewed papers in Machine Learning.

Research

- Presented a Spotlight talk at the Deep Learning Indaba 2019 slides.
- Presented a poster at the Deep Learning Indaba 2019 poster.
- Presentation on Neural Architecture Search for the Robotics, Autonomous Intelligence and Learning lab slides.
- Presented a poster at MLSS London, 2019.

Honours and Awards

Travel Award to attend Deep Learning Indaba

2019

Deep Learning Indaba

I received a travel grant and accomodation award to attend the Deep Learning Indaba in Kenya.

Full scholarship to attend MLSS London

2019

MLSS

I received a full scholarship to attend Machine Learning Summer Schools (MLSS) London. This competitive summer school had a 11.75 % acceptance rate (1,200 applicants for 140 places) and of 140 attendees, only 21 % were MSc students.

Postgraduate Merit Award

2019

University of Witwatersrand

Was awarded a Postgraduate Merit Award based on academic merit.

Academic Honorary Colours

2017

University of Pretoria

Was awarded Academic Honorary Colours by the Student Representative Council of the University of Pretoria.

Honours Cum Laude

2016

University of Pretoria

80.75 % Average for Honours in Computer Science.

Amazon Prize for Best Mobile Application - COS 301 Final Year Software Engineering Project 2015

Amazon, University of Pretoria

Project involved creating a website and Mobile App that uses Computer Vision to



Kale-ab Tessera

Machine Learning Engineer / Researcher



+27 766806878



kaleabtessera.com



kaleabtessera@gmail.com

About me —

Kale-ab is a young, bright and ambitious Machine Learning Engineer and Researcher. He is adaptable and open to learn new concepts in Machine Learning and AI in order to build on his previous knowledge. He considers a great work ethic and his ability to think innovatively as his greatest strengths.

Skills —

Deep Learning

Pytorch, Scikit-learn

Tensorflow, Keras

Flask, Django

Python

SQL,NoSQL

Amazon AWS, Google GCP

Mathematics, Quantitative Reasoning

(*)[The skill scale is from 0 (Fundamental Awareness) to 6 (Good Understanding).]

automatically identify and tag species of Stink Bugs.

Golden Key Honour Society

University of Pretoria

Was selected to join the Golden Key Honour Society as a result of being in the top 15% of my degree.

Merit Certificate for Leadership

2015

2013-2015

University of Pretoria

I received this reward for leadership during my time as a House Committee member at House Boekenhout.

Matric Academics 2012

PEPPS College

Notable achievements include being in the Top 1% of IEB IT Matric Students and receiving 7 Distinctions with an average of 87%.

Deputy-Head Boy 2012

PEPPS College

Was selected as deputy-head boy of my school in my matric year.

Academic Honours and Cultural Colours

2012

PEPPS College

Academic Honours were awarded for receiving Academic Colours (average above 80%) three years in a row. Cultural colours were awarded for excellence in various cultural activities such as chess and newspaper editing.

[Leadership]

- Secretary, Head of IT and Communications- Boekenhout Residence, University of Pretoria.
- Deputy-head boy PEPPS College.

Summer Schools

Deep Learning Indaba

2019

- I was the Front-End architect for the Applications system Baobab.
- I was selected as a tutor for the following advanced level practicals build your own TensorFlow, optimisation for deep learning, convolutional networks and recurrent neural networks.

MLSS London 2019

• The Machine Learning Summer School (MLSS) is a 12-day event where participants take intensive courses on a variety of topics in machine learning, ranging from optimization and Bayesian inference to deep learning, reinforcement learning and Gaussian processes (see topics).

Deep Learning Indaba

2017,2018.

 One week intensive Summer School covering state of the art techniques in Machine Learning and AI.

Experience

Machine Learning Specialist

April 2019 - Present

Multichoice

Modeling and predicting the the behaviour of over 15 million customers.

Intermediate Software Engineer

Oct 2017 - March 2019

Entelect

Full Stack Development:

- Front-End: React, Redux, Redux Saga, Jest and Enzyme.
- Integration Layer/Backend: Spring Boot, Maven.
- Databases: MongoDb.
- DevOps: Docker, Openshift, Jenkins, Linux.
- Data: I was tasked with managing a data catalog of tens of thousands of Mobile Phones (at Cell C). I had to collect this data from external sources via APIs, clean the data via automatic scripts, backup and recover the data using mongodump and provide search functionality on the data.



Kale-ab Tessera

Machine Learning Engineer / Researcher



+27 766806878



kaleabtessera.com



kaleabtessera@gmail.com

About me —

Kale-ab is a young, bright and ambitious Machine Learning Engineer and Researcher. He is adaptable and open to learn new concepts in Machine Learning and AI in order to build on his previous knowledge. He considers a great work ethic and his ability to think innovatively as his greatest strengths.

Skills —

Deep Learning

Pytorch, Scikit-learn

Tensorflow, Keras

Flask, Django

Python

SQL,NoSQL

Amazon AWS, Google GCP

Mathematics, Quantitative Reasoning

(*)[The skill scale is from 0 (Fundamental Awareness) to 6 (Good Understanding).]

Software Engineer

Jan 2016 - Oct 2017

Full Stack Development:

- Front-End: Angular JS 1, React and Redux.
- Integration Layer/Backend: .NET MVC 4.5.2, .Net Core 1.1 .
- Databases: SQL Server, MySql.
- DevOps: Amazon AWS EC2 and RDS instances, Web Servers (IIS).
- Data : I had to write advanced SQL stored procedures and functions, which ran efficiently on large data.

Internship

Sept 2015 - Nov 2015

RetroRabbit

RetroRabbit

Learned about various interesting topics including Source Control, Cloud Computing (Amazon AWS) and IoT.

2 weeks vacation work

July 2015 - July 2015

BBD

Requirements - Android Application, use of .NET MVC 4.5 Framework for the backend and management of a SQL Server database.

House Committee Member, Secretary, Head of IT and Communications

Sept 2014 - Sept 2015

University of Pretoria

I helped lead and mentor various residence, especially those who had academic difficulties and/or technical IT related issues.

Teaching Assistant, COS 212

Feb 2015 - Jun 2015

University of Pretoria

As a teaching assistant for Data Structures and Algorithms it was crucial to identify and recognize all the classical data structures; implement them in different ways; know how to measure the efficiency of implementations and algorithms.

Teaching Assistant, COS 110

Jul 2014 - Dec 2014

University of Pretoria

As a teaching assistant for Program design and Programming techniques, it was crucial to have good knowledge of object-oriented programming, inheritance, polymorphism, operator overloading, memory management and encapsulation.

Skills

- · Languages: Python, Java, Javascript, C#.
- Frameworks: Pytorch, Scikit-learn, Tensorflow, Keras, Flask, Django, Spring Boot, .Net Core, React.
- Devops: Amazon AWS (EC2 and RDS), GCP, Docker, Openshift, Jenkins, Linux.
- Databases: Mongo, SQL Server and MySql.

Online Courses

- · Introduction to Python for Data Science- Edx
- · Machine Learning by Stanford- Coursera